Hello again, welcome back and this lesson and we're going to be exploring inheritance,
which is TypeScript's way of letting us use one class, we'll use the logic of another.
We're going to learn how to use the extends keyword to build class hierarchies over
our behaviour and share common functionality across related objects.
First of all, let's understand what is inheritance.
In inheritance, let's one class extends the behaviour of another,
gaining access to its properties and methods along the way.
So I've got a class here, as you can see, called animal, and we just got a simple property called name,
and I've used a short hands way of using on the constructor, and we have a method called speak.
Now let's say we want to have a class called dog to extend the animal.
So class dog, let me use the extends keyword, so extends animal.
And now what we can do is we can over write the function that's been defined here,
and we can define it again specifically for our dog.
So we can do speak, and the speak method now returns,
let's have the tactics and foot, dollar this name box,
and we could have another class, so you can't extend any more.
We can also have the method which we're going to override of speak.
We're going to change this from bark to meow.
But both of these also still have the name property, which is inherited from the parent class
being animal. But in addition to this, we can also pick up the access of parent logic.
So for example, rather than having the actual, exactly the same
text here, what we can do inside here is we can use the super keyword.
So you could say super, speak, we could call that a function,
and we could then also add something else at the end, say for example meow.
So the super keyword allows us to call the parent class constructor or its methods,
which we've done in this particular example.
So this class here is called the child class, and the class at the top is called the parent class.
We've talked about using the super keyword to be able to access the methods to find on the
parent, but the child could also add an additional custom functionality, as well as overriding the
methods to find on the parent. Let's work through a little bit more a different example.
And let's create a class, a parent class called a vehicle.
We're going to have a constructor, and we're going to have a public property of make,
and another public property called model.
Let's just have a simple method on here called start.
And the method is just going to return.
Let's have let's say back text and say this make.
And this model is starting. Okay, so we've got some properties defined here.
We shouldn't of course have a code on here, that's what's complaining.
And now we can define another vehicle, so we can have an electric car, so electric
r, we can use the extends keyword extends vehicle.
And now we can have some natural properties that's only available on an electric car.
Perhaps it makes sense to have a battery level, so we can have battery level, which is a number.
We're going to default it to 100, which you can do with the equals. Now we can also have
an additional function, so we can call a charge, or create one called a charge,
and have return, be charging, which tactics, charging, dollar, this make, and this model to 100%.
Make sure I finish off the brackets here.
So you can see here that we have also got access to the methods here, so I could come in here
and I could do starts and I could override that if I particularly wanted to, or I could utilize it
when I'm creating an instance of that class, but in addition to that for electric car,
we've also added an additional property and it also got the extra custom functionality.
So inheritance lets us reuse logic and also build scalable class hierarchies.